"Why Vegans Should Eat
More Plant-Based"
In the United States, the #1 risk factor
for death is the American diet,
associated with more deaths
than any other risk factor,
responsible for like half a million
mothers, fathers, sisters, brothers,
friends, and family dying every year
because of what they ate,
mostly from cardiovascular disease.
That's where plant-based
diets can come in,
associated with lower risk of
developing cardiovascular disease,
lower risk of dying from
cardiovascular disease,
and, in fact, a lower risk of dying
from all causes put together.
Progressively increasing
the intake of plant foods
by reducing the amount
of intake of animal foods
may enable us to live
longer, healthier lives.
And it doesn't take much.
If you look at the largest cohort
study on diet and health in history,
the NIH-AARP study, they found
that replacing just 3% of energy
from animal protein with plant
protein was associated
with a 10% lower overall mortality
in both men and women.
Of all the animal protein sources,
eggs were the worst.
Swapping in 3% plant protein
for egg protein was associated
with twice the benefit, exceeding 20%
lower mortality in men and women.
The researchers concluded that
the study provides evidence
for public health recommendations
regarding dietary modifications
in terms of choice of protein sources
that may promote health and longevity,
and plant protein is preferable.
Now, healthy plant-based
diets are associated
with lower risk of all-cause mortality,
but with an emphasis on healthy.
When individuals increase their
consumption of plant foods
while decreasing their
intake of animal foods,
there could be an increase in their
consumption of less-healthy options:
highly processed plant foods
like Coke and Wonder Bread.
One cannot assume that
simply avoiding animal foods
will necessarily produce
such a healthy diet.
In order to distinguish between
healthful and unhealthful vegan diets,
the term "whole food, plant-based diet"
is attributed
to Cornell Professor Emeritus
in Nutritional Biochemistry,
Dr. T. Colin Campbell.
If you look at India, for example,
you see a decreasing
in whole plant food content
of their diets,
along with increasing
risk of obesity
and noncommunicable
chronic diseases.
This may help explain why
disease rates are on the rise
even in a country with
a large vegetarian contingent.
This may help explain why
health-wise vegans in the US
do better than vegans in the UK.
The #1 reason people in the US
eat plant-based is health,
and so they eat more plants,
more fiber, vitamin C ---
only found concentrated
in whole plant foods.
Whereas the #1 reason given
in the UK is animal welfare reasons,
and so they may be more likely to just
switch over to vegan doughnuts.
You can't know if vegans really
have to eat more plants though
until you put it to the test.
An evaluation of an 8-week
whole food plant-based
lifestyle modification program
in which two dozen were already
eating vegetarian or vegan,
but not necessarily
whole food plant-based.
And after 8 weeks, even
those who already started out
vegetarian or vegan experienced
significant weight loss
and reductions in cholesterol.
They lost ten pounds and dropped
their LDL cholesterol 15 points.
So even a short-term whole food
plant-based dietary intervention
may provide significant benefits
for non-vegetarians, vegetarians,
and vegans alike.
We have a food supply
in which "junk" is a food group,
willfully engineered
to maximize eating for profit,
and the industry will happily make all
the vegan junk we're willing to buy.
In fact, if you compare the consumption
of ultra-processed junk
across different eating patterns,
vegetarians and vegans were found
to be eating the most junk,
like potato chips and cookies.
Not all plant-based foods exert
the same health effects.
But what about animal food?
These researchers
separately scored
the quality of different
plant-based foods
with a plant-based
Diet Quality Index,
and also various animal foods
in an animal-based
Diet Quality Index.
For example, if you'd consider
processed meats and red meats
as unhealthy animal foods,
but fish, seafood, dairy, and
poultry as healthy animal foods --
and you throw eggs in
with the unhealthy, too,
based on the most recent evidence --
they found that the higher
quality of plant foods,
the longer you live,
the lower all-cause mortality.
But no independent association was
found for the quality of animal foods,
meaning they all seemed just as bad
in terms of cancer mortality,
heart disease mortality,
and all-cause mortality.
In light of the expanding global
threat of cardiovascular disease,
large-scale shifts toward healthy
plant-based diets are imperative
to ensure future human health.
But all plant foods
are not created equal.